Changes in your diet not
only affect you physically,
physiologically inside,
but also mentally,
how well you think,
psychologically,
how well you feel.
But you’ll never know just
how good you can feel
until you put it to the test
and try eating healthy.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
You know I talk a lot about
the killers in our food,
but what happens when
we are the food?
Today we ponder the pros and cons
of repelling mosquitoes with DEET.
The most dangerous animal in
the world isn't the Great White,
or the King Cobra, or lions
and tigers and bears.
In fact, only about 10 people die
in shark attacks every year.
Coming in #2 as most dangerous?
Fellow human beings.
But the worst?
Mosquitoes.
Literally billions of people
are at risk
of contracting dengue fever
from mosquitoes,
and hundreds of thousands die from
mosquito-borne malaria every year.
New threats like Zika continue
to pose a global public health threat,
such that the World Health Organization
suggested delaying pregnancy
in Zika-affected areas
around the world.
What's the best mosquito
repellent to wear?
There are products like permethrin,
a product originally derived from
chrysanthemums interestingly,
that can be applied to clothes,
but what about repellents
you actually put on your skin?
DEET is the repellent to beat,
considered the gold standard
of protection when it's
crucial not to get bitten.
It was developed back in the
It's long been considered
the first-line mosquito repellent.
Effectiveness-wise 20% to 50%
DEET repellents
provide up to several
hours of protection.
That's rubbed on the skin, though.
DEET-impregnated wristbands
don't work, repelling mosquitoes
only from areas
covered by the band,
which I guess you could say about
non-DEET-impregnated wristbands.
DEET or citronella wristbands
have been clocked at working
more broadly for only
Safety-wise, DEET
is considered safe
even in the second
and third trimesters
of pregnancy,
and in children as long as
they're older than two months.
Now it should be noted that
DEET can damage plastics
and synthetic materials;
therefore, care should
be taken when it's used
around plastic watches, eyeglasses,
and synthetic fabrics.
Nylon is okay, but it's been found
to damage spandex, rayon, acetate,
and pigmented leather,
in addition to plastic and vinyl.
DEET is absorbed through your
skin into your bloodstream,
but it's cleared from your system
within a few hours.
Does it have any adverse effects?
DEET is probably far less toxic
than many people believe.
DEET has a remarkable safety profile
after now more than a half century
of use and billions of applications.
Fewer than 50 cases of serious
toxic effects have been documented
in the medical literature since 1960,
and most of them resolved.
Most reported cases of adverse
or lethal events involved overuse
or incorrect use of the product --
incorrect use as in chugging
it to commit suicide.
What's a correct usage?
Read and follow all directions
on the product label.
Only apply to intact
non-irritated skin.
Do not apply near
eyes and mouth
and only sparingly
around ears.
That's to avoid accidental
eye exposure or ingestion.
It can be applied to the face,
but don't spray it in your face.
Spray it on your hands
and then you can dab on,
but still avoid the eyes and mouth.
Apply it to children
so they don't swallow any.
Just use enough to
cover exposed skin
or on the outside of clothing,
not underneath.
And then once you're back inside,
wash it off with soap and water,
and wash any treated clothing.
If you do have a reaction,
stop using it, wash it off,
call your local poison control center.
And if you go to your doctor,
bring the bottle.
So which mosquito repellent
works best?
Well, in head-to-head tests,
DEET crushed it.
But this was in reference to a study
published about 20 years ago.
Anything new on the market that
won't melt your eyeglasses?
We'll find out next.
DEET has been considered the most
effective mosquito repellent.
Unquestionably, read this editorial
in The Journal of Family Practice,
it should be the only
mosquito repellent recommended
by physicians, with no other
repellent coming close.
Given the dramatic efficacy,
it's hard to conceive that any
other repellent would ever beat it.
However, there are some rare reports
of severe reactions to DEET,
not the mention the fact that it can
melt plastics, like eyeglass frames
and cellphone components,
and many consumers find the odor
and sensation on the skin unpleasant.
Enter picaridin. Overall, studies
have shown little difference
between DEET and picaridin
applied at the same dosage,
with some evidence pointing to
a superior persistence for picaridin,
all without the irritancy, odor,
and melted glasses.
No wonder it got
Consumer Reports pick
for the best overall insect repellent.
Note that concentration matters.
Their 20% picaridin product
topped the list,
but at 5% it was one of their
worst performing products.
Any toxicity?
Adverse effects, when occurring,
primarily manifested as
eye irritation/redness,
vomiting, and oral irritation,
but of course you're not supposed
to eat it or spray it in your eyes.
But even unintentional ingestion
was associated
with only relatively minor toxicity.
What about the electronic
mosquito repellent gizmos?
Ten studies done, and all ten found
that there was no difference
in the number of mosquitoes landing
on people with or without the gizmos
and experiments out
in the field confirm:
no effect on preventing
mosquito bites.
Picaridin was roughly based
on a black pepper compound,
but like DEET is
a synthetic chemical.
Are there any natural repellents?
Of course, just because
something is natural
does' t mean it's necessarily safe.
Strychnine is a natural product
of the strychnine tree,
and ricin from castor beans
is 10,000 times deadlier still.
In fact, the top 10 most toxic
poisons are all natural.
But let's look at the mosquito
repellent effects
of about 20 essential oils
compared to a placebo
control group and to DEET.
Only five had any
lasting effect at all.
Peppermint and lemongrass oil
were effective for 30 minutes.
Spearmint and garlic oil
started working
but didn't even last that long.
Cinnamon oil, though,
reduced mosquito attraction
for one and a half hours.
The remaining essential oils
had no significant effect
on mosquito attraction at any time
point, and this includes citronella.
Citronella was the most widely used
repellent before DEET was invented,
and is still used today
in many formulations
despite inferior efficacy.
At lower concentrations,
it may only last a few minutes,
and at higher concentrations
citronella can cause skin irritation.
Compared to a complete protection
time of 6 hours for DEET,
citronella may only
last 10-1/2 minutes.
Therefore, citronella
may be acceptable
for brief exposure
to nuisance mosquitoes,
but it is not advised for protection
if you really can't afford to get bit.
Essential oils, read this family
medicine journal editorial,
have no effectiveness
and are not recommended.
But that was before we learned
about lemon eucalyptus,
the only plant-based repellent
recommended by the CDC,
though should not be used
by pregnant women
or children younger
than three years of age.
Consumer Reports listed it
as one of their top three picks,
warding off mosquitoes and ticks
for at least seven hours.
All the other botanical products
they tested failed.
But 40% lemon eucalyptus was shown
to prevent bites for 4 to 7 hours
after application for aggressive
species of mosquitos
and for greater than 12 hours
for less aggressive mosquitoes,
a period of prevention greater than
at least a 10% DEET repellent.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the NutritionFacts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and the “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.